SCALA FUNCTIONAL DEVELOPER

□ (+39) 333/3341324 | ■ toniogela89@mail.com | ♠ toniogela.dev | □ TonioGela | □ toniogela |

"In order to understand recursion, one must first understand recursion"

Professional Summary _____

I'm a **Scala** developer with a passion for creating elegant solutions. As a backend programmer with five years of career experience, I have developed fast and reliable applications. I am a **self-learner**: I have started a career as a programmer despite it not being the core of my academic education. In my training as a **physicist**, I have acquired skills that allow me to have a different view of the problems. I am a Scala enthusiast, willing to contribute as much as possible to the OSS community. I **keep studying** to enhance my knowledge and open up to new **libraries/technologies** in my spare time. Currently, I'm in love with **Cats Effect** and all the other **Typelevel**'s projects.

Experience

LastMinute.com Chiasso, Switzerland

SCALA SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT - DATA ARCHITECT SPECIALIST

Dec. 2019 - Present

- In order to improve performances and fault tolerance I redesigned an application that was heavily relying on Avro serde, converting the whole process in a *Array*[*Byte*] => *Array*[*Byte*] mapping, clustering it using Akka plus its **Grpc** communication module and deploying it on **Google Cloud Platform**.
- I implemented an optimized MySql to Vertica replicator that reads and deserializes binlogs discarding the useless operations. It uses ANTLR to parse the MySql grammar to create the AST used as internal representation for the DDL statements. The internal data structure used to hold DML transactional data is an Adaptive Radix Tree.
- Every project was developed in conjuction with at least one junior colleague, in order to **mentor** about Scala, FP, cloud technologies, application design, etc.

Bitrock s.r.l. Milan, Italy

SCALA SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

Dec. 2018 - Dec. 2019

- For a telco customer I contributed to develop a real time radio towers' kpi monitoring application using **Spark** and **Scala**. The application main goal is to process a big amount of data to check if some quality threshold has been exceeded and to raise an alarm. Using Cats to implement the validation logic and functional error handling of the configuration companion microservice has been the most intriguing challenge.
- I built a POC using **Kafka Streams** Scala API to monitor and process in real time a **WebSocket** channel of geolocalized events to produce aggregated information and metrics.

FacilityLive OpCo S.r.l. Pavia, Italy

JAVA SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

Jan. 2017 - Dec. 2018

- I have been solely responsible for the development of more than 10 **Microservices** using **Spring Boot**. This microservices represented the connection and orchestration layer between a custom search engine platform deployed on **Kubernetes** and the data processing layer developed using **Spark** and deployed on **Mesos**. Every customization of the multi tenant application had to trigger a Spark job responsible of producing **Lucene** indexes whose search engine custom search was based on.
- I participated in the creation and design of a data parser that included an **HTML crawler/spider** using **Akka** to gather metadata to be used as search engine indexes.

SDG Consulting s.r.l.

Milan, Italy

BIG DATA ANALYST

Jun. 2016 - Jan. 2017

- I was the responsible for the design, installation and the maintenance of **IBM Watson Explorer** Products (the entire BlueMix Suite) for banks, pharma and telco customers.
- I have migrated 10000+ store procedures from Microsoft SQL Server 2008 to IBM PureData forAnalytics for a client, in order to reduce query execution times by an order of 3 magnitudes.



SCALA/JAVA STACK

- · Cats and many Typelevel libraries, whole Akka suite
- Solid Knowledge of JVM Internals and Scala Type System
- · Various RDBMS & NoSQL DBs APIs, Serialization Algorithms, Communication Protocols, Build Tools, etc

OTHER

- · Solid Knowledge of both Functional Programming methodologies and Object Oriented Design Patterns
- Very interested in Category Theory and theoretical aspects behind functional programming
- Kafka, Kafka Streams
- Big fan of **Test Driven Development** methodologies
- Currently studying for **LFCS** certification
- Currently studying Rust and Haskell
- · Well aware of Agile methodologies

SOFT SKILLS

- Very good **relationals skills** and good team mate used to work in 10+ members remote team
- Able to work in high stress, fast paced, and dynamic situations even **under pressure** or close to a delivery
- Ability to solve problems in a **fast** and **reliable** way, or to address them to the correct person
- Self learner with a passion for mentoring and training people
- · Great communities lover and participant

LANGUAGES

- C1 Proficiency English
- Italian Native Speaker
- · A1 Certified Greek, B1 Proficiency

Certifications

LIGHTBEND

- · Lightbend Scala Language Professional Level 1
- · Lightbend Akka for Scala Professional Level 1
- · Lightbend Akka Streams for Scala Professional Level 1

Presentations

LESSONS/PRESENTATIONS

Practical Typeclasses @ JUG MiTo (Italian)

Teaching

University of Pavia LESSONS/PRESENTATIONS

Pavia, Italy

2018 - 2019

- Presentation "Basic Informatics, Coding and Tech Languages" at Technological Innovation and Law Winter School (TIL 2019)
- Series of 2 "Programming Basics" lessons for the "Law, Science and New Technologies" class

Education

University of Pavia

BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN PHYSICS

Pavia, Italy

2008 - 2016

- Thesis Title: Entropic sampling in spin sistems
- · Developed code for numerical simulation of high-interacting spin systems in Potts' model